A Guide to the Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection, 1926-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection, 1926-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Carter, H. G.; Lee, Hyo Keun; Scott, Charles W.; Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium [Burkeville, VA]
Ms2019-009
0.3 Cubic Feet 1 box
The Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection includes materials from 1926-1971. The collection contains information relating to the operation of the sanatorium from 1918-1965. The collection contains administrative papers, published works of doctors, ephemera, and images.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2018.
Scope and Content
The Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection includes materials from 1926-1971. The collection contains information relating to the operation of the sanatorium from 1918-1965. The collection consists of three series: Administrative Papers, Ephemera, and Images.
Arrangement
The Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) Collection is arranged in three series: Administrative Papers, Ephemera, and Images.
I. Administrative Papers contains the following items: different versions and revisions of "A Brief History of Piedmont Sanatorium", administrative documents (including patient population and drug lists), bulletins, and published papers by staff. This series is arranged by material type. Within each folder, materials are in chronological order.
II. Ephemera contains newspaper clippings, materials relating to the graduation of nurses, and a story entitled "Adventures in a Wheelchair." This series is arranged by material type. Within each folder, materials are in chronological order.
III. Images contains stamps and postcards with pictures of the sanatorium. There is also a photograph of staff. This series is arranged by material type. Within each folder, materials are in chronological order.
Historical Note
The Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Burkeville, Virginia) was a hospital open to African-Americans in order to treat tuberculosis from 1917-1965. Shortly after the sanatorium opened, a two-year school for training African-American nurses was opened.
Index Terms
Subjects:
African American history; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Medicine
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Papers, 1926-1971
  - A Brief History of the Piedmont Tuberculosis Sanatorium (variations), 1949-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Documents, 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1926-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Published Papers by Staff, 1959. d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Ephemera, 1949-1965
  - Newspaper Clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Materials Relating to Graduation of Nurses, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Adventures in a Wheelchair" Story, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: Images, 1928-1958
  - Stamps and Postcards, 1928-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)